# MARTIN SCHUESSLER

HCI Researcher in Explainable Artificial Intelligence

49 (0) 1757632474 @ me@mschuessler.de @ mschuessler.de

Berlin, Germany



#### RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research lies at the intersection of Human-Computer interaction and Explainable Artificial Intelligence. I currently investigate how explanation techniques can improve users understanding of highly complex computer vision models. I also critically analyse how datasets and models for computer vision are created to make suggestions about more intelligible, value complaint and ethical usage of Al systems. I am a mixed-methods researcher, employing a wide range of methods including quantitative methods from Psychology and qualitative methods from Sociology.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# PhD Candidate | Research Fellow

Criticality of Al Research Group, Weizenbaum Institute # 01/2018 - Ongoing ♥ TU Berlin, Berlin, Germany

As part of a newly formed interdisciplinary research group, my research focuses on empirical studies in the field of explainable artificial intelligence (XAI). I currently conduct human-grounded evaluations of gradient based attribution methods, example-based explanations and invertible neural nets.

- Several interdisciplinary publications with machine learning experts, legal scholars and social scientist
- CSCW '20 Best Paper award for interdisciplinary paper
- Phttps://vernetzung-und-gesellschaft.de

# Visiting Researcher

**UCL Interaction Centre** 

In a virtual collaboration with my co-supervisor Enrico Costanza, I focus on the user evaluation and potential improvement of explanation algorithms for image classification applications of CNNs.

- Designed a user study evaluating the performance of "saliency maps" together with Ahmed Algaraawi
- Co-authered IUI '20 full paper
- Phttps://uclic.ucl.ac.uk/

# Java Programmer

Osyon GmbH 

Java Software development for a Europe-wide operating laboratory group

#### Student Assistant Researcher

HPI - Stanford Design Thinking Research Program **10/2015 - 09/2016** ♥ HPI, Potsdam, Germany

I was part of the Visual Diagnostics Team which is working on developing and evaluating diagnostic instruments for design team interaction.

- Advised the team on evaluation methods and statistical analysis with R
- Facilitated data acquisition and data cleaning by developing and maintaining a data management system
- https://hpi.de/en/dtrp/program/overview.html

# Student Assistant Researcher

Mobile and Physical Interaction Group, Q&U Lab **1** 04/2014 - 03/2016 ♥ TU Berlin, Berlin, Germany

Under the lead of Prof. Jörg Müller, our group contributed to CHI, UIST, UBICOMP and CSCW.

- Implemented an advanced peephole display on iOS devices
- Designed and conducted 4 small scale studies on peephole displays
- Conducted experiments and contributed to UbiComp '15 full paper
- Taught 40 undergrad students how to code in C
- http://qu.tu-berlin.de/menue/forschung/gruppen/mobile\_physical\_interacti Ð

### **EDUCATION**

### M. Sc. Computer Science

TU Berlin

- Grade: 1.3 (GPA: 3.8)
- Mayor in HCI (communication-based systems) courses incl.: usability engineering, multimodal interaction, augmented reality and python for Machine Learning
- Minor in empirical social science courses incl.: survey methodology, ethnography, and statistics
- Thesis: Spatial Input for 2D Peephole Navigation on Mobile Devices

# Study Abroad Program

University of Sydney

### B. Sc. Business Informatics

Otto-von-Guericke University

- Major in computer science and Minor in economics
- Bachelor thesis published as CHI 2014 paper

# **SKILLS**

#### Research Methods

Lab Studies User Research

Online Studies Literature Surveys

Participatory Observations Surveys

Qualitative Interviews

# Programming

R (tidyverse) Python Obj-C Java

Matlab SQL Git

Creative Tools

Video Editing Rapid Prototyping

Design Thinking

# **CERTIFICATES**

Certificate in Advanced English (C1)

Design Thinking Basic Track

GDPR Specialist (ISQI)

#### STRENGTHS

# Research and Development Assistant

Telekom Innovation Laboratories

01/2013 - 03/2014

▼ T-Labs, Berlin, Germany

T-Labs innovates in close cooperation with science and industry. Supervised by Mehran Roshandel and Dr. Hamed Ketabdar I enhanced a real time monitoring and outlier detection system (called ADIT).

- Developed and evaluated a new spectral analysis algorithm in Matlab
- Implemented the algorithm in Java as a component for ADIT
- Conducted extensive testing and parameter optimization
- http://www.laboratories.telekom.com/public/Deutsch/Innovation/Pages/Cr oss-Domain-Middleware.aspx

#### **Graduate Assistant**

Department of Simulation and Graphics

**#** 06/2010 - 06/2012

Otto-von-Guericke University, Magdeburg, Germany

Working on "Sugar" (One Laptop per Child Human Interface)

# IT-Consultant

Self employed

Setup and maintenance of e-commerce, content management and database management systems (7 projects)

#### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

# Between Subjectivity and Imposition: Power Dynamics in Data **Annotation for Computer Vision**

CSCW '20 - Best Paper Award - Full Paper

M. Miceli, M. Schuessler, T. Yang

# Evaluating saliency map explanations for convolutional neural networks: a user study

IUI '20 - Full Paper

A. Algaraawi, M. Schuessler, P. Weiß, E. Costanza, N. Berthouze

# A Taxonomy for Human Subject Evaluation of Black-Box **Explanations in XAI**

IUI '20 - ExSS Workshop Paper

M. Chromik, M. Schuessler

# Minimalistic Explanations: Capturing the Essence of Decisions

CHI '19 - Late Breaking Work

M. Schuessler, P. Weiß

# Analyzing Visual Attention During Whole Body Interaction with **Public Displays**

UbiComp '15 - Full Paper

R. Walter, A. Bullling, D. Lindlbauer, M. Schuessler, J. Müller

# Pinch-drag-flick vs. spatial input: rethinking zoom & pan on mobile displays

CHI '14 - Full Paper

M. Spindler, M. Schuessler, M. Martsch, R. Dachselt

## 04/2014 Phttp://mschuessler.de/pub/CHI14.pdf

# Analytical & Inquisitive

Seven years in research taught me to approach challenging problems methodically and persistently. I constantly strive for new insights and skills.



# Teaching

Passionate about facilitating the exchange of knowledge, I acquired the ability to explain complex things in simple words.



# Interpersonal and Interdisciplinary Communication

I am an extrovert, who mediates between different jargons in multi-disciplinary teams.



# Self-organized and proactive

Working on a dissertation with remote teams worldwide taught me to organise my work needing little supervision.

#### **PASSIONS**



VW T3 Camper Van



**DIY Projects** 



Reducing Air Travel

# ACADEMIC SERVICE

### Reviewer

CHI '20

# **Program Committee**

ExSS Workshop @ IUI '20

### Student Volunteer

ITS '14, UIST '18, CHI '19, CHI '20\*